Since we've done some questions about net
forces
on friction, we're going to visit some
that
include normal force as well, and these
questions
are a bit challenging, and they really
make
you think of how to do them. So we have a
kilogram box is placed on a horizontal
floor
inside the elevator. The elevator is
moving
upwards and is slowing down at a constant
rate
of 1.5 metres per second.
So let's say we have an elevator over
here.
Let's just say it's the ground. This would
be
the elevator. And we have a 12 kilogram
box
over here. The elevator itself is moving
upwards,
and it's slowing down at a constant rate
of
1.8 metres per second squared. Draw a
labelled
full body diagram for the box.
Well, before we draw a full body diagram
for
the box, let's first try to visualise it,
because
this question is mostly about
visualisation.
So let's draw a full body diagram for the
elevator
first. Let's
assume that the elevator is slowing down
purely
because of gravity. It really does not
matter
if there's breaks or if it's just slowing
down
because of gravity, but what we do know is
that
there is a net force acting downwards.
Even if it's going up, since it's
accelerating
downwards, that means that there must be a
net
force downwards. Do you agree? Because
force
is mass times acceleration. If we know
that
it's slowing down at a constant rate, that
means
that there's a force downwards that's
constant.
So now we know that, we can use that
information
to solve our problem.
First of all, our free-body diagram of the
box.
Let's do it. So, first of all, we always
have
gravity. So, F of G.
Next, we have the normal force. However,
in
this case, since the elevator is already
slowing
down, the normal force is going to be
actually
less. And it's going to be less by the
magnitude
of this de-acceleration force over here, F
normal. Because all of this force is going
to
counteract the gravity here, so that
leaves
less force for the surface to push back
because
the surface is actually experiencing a
force
downwards. So, if the surface is
experiencing
a force downwards, that means the net
force
is going to be less. So, now let's
determine
the direction of the acceleration of the
elevator
and the box. Well, acceleration would be
downwards.
That is given in the question, and if the
elevator
is accelerating downwards, then the box
will
also be accelerating downwards as it's
going
in the same direction. So, B, the answer
is
just downwards. Third one, calculate the
magnitude
of the normal force exerted by the floor
on
the box. Well, we know that we need to
first find the normal force.
The normal force is equal to, in this
case,
the force of gravity minus the net
de-acceleration
the box has over here.
So, we're going to have Fg minus F
net. Like I said, it's because this
cancels
out with some of the normal force. What
is Fg? Well, Fg is just mass times 9.81
minus F net is mass times the
acceleration,
which is negative 1.80.
This should also be negative. So, the
normal
force would just be negative 9.81 plus
1.80.
What is the mass?
Well, we know it's 12 kilograms. Times 1
point,
we plug this in, plus 1.8, and we're going
to
get negative 8.01. 8.01.
And if you multiply that by the mass,
we're
going to get negative 96.12 newtons.
And that will be the normal force.
And now, of course, you have to round it
to
3 sig figs because the mass is 3 sig figs,
so
the final answer will be actually negative
96.1
newtons. And that's it for a bit of extra
practice
on dynamics, net forces, and free body
diagrams.
Remember, always remember to draw your
free
body diagrams to help you visualize what's
happening.
Then try to get the net force, or whatever
the
force the question wants, and after you
get
the net force, you have basically solved
the
entire problem. And there are only a few
next
steps you have to do in order to
completely
solve the problem. Thank you for watching,
and
I hope you enjoyed this unit.